<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Resources>
    <string id ="1">
        <en>Happy is the one who has not followed the counsel of the wicked,
or taken the path of sinners,
or joined the company of the insolent;
rather, this one delights in GOD?s teaching,
and studies that teaching day and night.
Such a one is like a tree planted beside streams of water,
which yields its fruit in season,
whose foliage never fades,
and whatever it produces thrives.
Not so the wicked;
rather, they are like chaff that wind blows away.
Therefore the wicked will not survive judgment,
nor will sinners, in the assembly of the righteous.
For GOD cherishes the way of the righteous,
but the way of the wicked is doomed.
</en>
        <he>אַ֥שְֽׁרֵי־הָאִ֗ישׁ אֲשֶׁ֤ר ׀ לֹ֥א הָלַךְ֮ בַּעֲצַ֢ת רְשָׁ֫עִ֥ים וּבְדֶ֣רֶךְ חַ֭טָּאִים לֹ֥א עָמָ֑ד וּבְמוֹשַׁ֥ב לֵ֝צִ֗ים לֹ֣א יָשָֽׁב׃ כִּ֤י אִ֥ם־בְּתוֹרַ֥ת יְהֹוָ֗ה חֶ֫פְצ֥וֹ וּֽבְתוֹרָת֥וֹ יֶהְגֶּ֗ה יוֹמָ֥ם וָלָֽיְלָה׃ וְֽהָיָ֗ה כְּעֵץ֮ שָׁת֢וּל עַֽל־פַּלְגֵ֫י־מָ֥יִם אֲשֶׁ֤ר פִּרְי֨וֹ ׀ יִתֵּ֬ן בְּעִתּ֗וֹ וְעָלֵ֥הוּ לֹֽא־יִבּ֑וֹל וְכֹ֖ל אֲשֶׁר־יַעֲשֶׂ֣ה יַצְלִֽיחַ׃ לֹא־כֵ֥ן הָרְשָׁעִ֑ים כִּ֥י אִם־כַּ֝מֹּ֗ץ אֲֽשֶׁר־תִּדְּפֶ֥נּוּ רֽוּחַ׃ עַל־כֵּ֤ן ׀ לֹא־יָקֻ֣מוּ רְ֭שָׁעִים בַּמִּשְׁפָּ֑ט וְ֝חַטָּאִ֗ים בַּעֲדַ֥ת צַדִּיקִֽים׃ כִּֽי־יוֹדֵ֣עַ יְ֭הֹוָה דֶּ֣רֶךְ צַדִּיקִ֑ים וְדֶ֖רֶךְ רְשָׁעִ֣ים תֹּאבֵֽד</he>
        <trans>Ashrê haish asher lo halach baatsat reshaim, uvdérech chataim lo amad, uvmoshav letsim lo iashav
Ki im betorat Adonai chef?tso uvtorato iegue iomam valaila
Vehaia keets shatul al palguê máyim, asher pirio yiten beito vealehu lo yibol, vechol asher iaasse iats?líach
Lo chen hareshaim, ki im camots asher tidefenu rúach
Al ken lo iacúmu reshaim bamishpat, vechataim baadat tsadikim
Ki iodêa Adonai dérech tsadikim, vedérech reshaim toved

</trans>
</string>
    
    <string id ="2">
        <en>Why do nations assemble,
and peoples plot vain things;
kings of the earth take their stand,
and regents intrigue together
against the one anointed by GOD?
?Let us break the cords of their yoke,
shake off their ropes from us!?
The One who is enthroned in heaven laughs;
my Sovereign mocks at them.
Then [God] speaks to them in anger,
terrifying them with divine rage,
?But I have installed My king
on Zion, My holy mountain!?
Let me tell of the decree:
 GOD said to me,
?You are My son,
I have fathered you this day.
Ask it of Me,
and I will make the nations your domain;
your estate, the limits of the earth.
You can smash them with an iron mace,
shatter them like potter?s ware.?
So now, O kings, be prudent;
accept discipline, you rulers of the earth!
Serve GOD in awe;
tremble with fright, pay homage in good faith,
lest [God] be angered, and your way be doomed
in the mere flash of divine anger.
Happy are all who take refuge in [God].
</en>
        <he>לָ֭מָּה רָגְשׁ֣וּ גוֹיִ֑ם וּ֝לְאֻמִּ֗ים יֶהְגּוּ־רִֽיק׃ יִ֥תְיַצְּב֨וּ ׀ מַלְכֵי־אֶ֗רֶץ וְרוֹזְנִ֥ים נֽוֹסְדוּ־יָ֑חַד עַל־יְ֝הֹוָ֗ה וְעַל־מְשִׁיחֽוֹ׃ נְֽ֭נַתְּקָה אֶת־מֽוֹסְרוֹתֵ֑ימוֹ וְנַשְׁלִ֖יכָה מִמֶּ֣נּוּ עֲבֹתֵֽימוֹ׃ יוֹשֵׁ֣ב בַּשָּׁמַ֣יִם יִשְׂחָ֑ק אֲ֝דֹנָ֗י יִלְעַג־לָֽמוֹ׃ אָ֤ז יְדַבֵּ֣ר אֵלֵ֣ימוֹ בְאַפּ֑וֹ וּֽבַחֲרוֹנ֥וֹ יְבַהֲלֵֽמוֹ׃ וַ֭אֲנִי נָסַ֣כְתִּי מַלְכִּ֑י עַל־צִ֝יּ֗וֹן הַר־קׇדְשִֽׁי׃ אֲסַפְּרָ֗ה אֶֽ֫ל־חֹ֥ק יְֽהֹוָ֗ה אָמַ֘ר־אֵלַ֥י בְּנִ֥י אַ֑תָּה אֲ֝נִ֗י הַיּ֥וֹם יְלִדְתִּֽיךָ׃ שְׁאַ֤ל מִמֶּ֗נִּי וְאֶתְּנָ֣ה ג֭וֹיִם נַחֲלָתֶ֑ךָ וַ֝אֲחֻזָּתְךָ֗ אַפְסֵי־אָֽרֶץ׃ תְּ֭רֹעֵם בְּשֵׁ֣בֶט בַּרְזֶ֑ל כִּכְלִ֖י יוֹצֵ֣ר תְּנַפְּצֵֽם׃ וְ֭עַתָּה מְלָכִ֣ים הַשְׂכִּ֑ילוּ הִ֝וָּסְר֗וּ שֹׁ֣פְטֵי אָֽרֶץ׃ עִבְד֣וּ אֶת־יְהֹוָ֣ה בְּיִרְאָ֑ה וְ֝גִ֗ילוּ בִּרְעָדָֽה׃ נַשְּׁקוּ־בַ֡ר פֶּן־יֶאֱנַ֤ף ׀ וְתֹ֬אבְדוּ דֶ֗רֶךְ כִּֽי־יִבְעַ֣ר כִּמְעַ֣ט אַפּ֑וֹ אַ֝שְׁרֵ֗י כׇּל־ח֥וֹסֵי בֽוֹ׃</he>
        <trans>Lama ragueshu goyim, uleumim iegu ric
Yiteiatsevu malchê érets, verozenim nossedu iachad, al Adonai veal meshicho      
Nenateca et mosserotêmo, venashlicha mimenu avotêmo
Ioshev bashamayim yis'chac, Adonai yil'ag lamo
Az iedaber elêmo veapo, uvacharono ievahalêmo
Vaani nassachti malki, al Tsión harcodshi
Assapera el choc Adonai amar elai beni áta, ani haiom ielidtícha
Sheal mimeni veetená goyim nachalatêcha, vaachuzatechá afsê árets
Teroem beshévet barzel, kich'li iotser tenapetsem
Veata melachim haskilu, hivasseru shofetê árets
Ivdu et Adonai beyir'á, veguilu bir'ada
Nashecu var, pen ieenaf vetovedu dérech, ki yiv'ar kim'at apô, ashrê col chossê vo</trans>
</string>
    
    <string id ="3">
        <en>A psalm of David when he fled from his son Absalom.
O ETERNAL One, my foes are so many!
Many are those who attack me;
many say of me,
?There is no deliverance for him through God.?    Selah.
But You, O ETERNAL One, are a shield about me,
my glory, who holds my head high.
I cry aloud to GOD,
who answers me from the holy mountain.    Selah.
I lie down and sleep and wake again,
for GOD sustains me.
I have no fear of the myriad forces
arrayed against me on every side.
Rise, O ETERNAL One!
Deliver me, O my God!
For You slap all my enemies in the face;
You break the teeth of the wicked.
Deliverance is GOD?s;
Your blessing be upon Your people!    Selah.
</en>
        <he>מִזְמ֥וֹר לְדָוִ֑ד בְּ֝בׇרְח֗וֹ מִפְּנֵ֤י ׀ אַבְשָׁל֬וֹם בְּנֽוֹ׃ יְ֭הֹוָה מָה־רַבּ֣וּ צָרָ֑י רַ֝בִּ֗ים קָמִ֥ים עָלָֽי׃ רַבִּים֮ אֹמְרִ֢ים לְנַ֫פְשִׁ֥י אֵ֤ין יְֽשׁוּעָ֓תָה לּ֬וֹ בֵאלֹהִ֬ים סֶֽלָה׃ וְאַתָּ֣ה יְ֭הֹוָה מָגֵ֣ן בַּעֲדִ֑י כְּ֝בוֹדִ֗י וּמֵרִ֥ים רֹאשִֽׁי׃ ק֭וֹלִי אֶל־יְהֹוָ֣ה אֶקְרָ֑א וַיַּעֲנֵ֨נִי מֵהַ֖ר קׇדְשׁ֣וֹ סֶֽלָה׃ אֲנִ֥י שָׁכַ֗בְתִּי וָאִ֫ישָׁ֥נָה הֱקִיצ֑וֹתִי כִּ֖י יְהֹוָ֣ה יִסְמְכֵֽנִי׃ לֹֽא־אִ֭ירָא מֵרִבְב֥וֹת עָ֑ם אֲשֶׁ֥ר סָ֝בִ֗יב שָׁ֣תוּ עָלָֽי׃ ק֘וּמָ֤ה יְהֹוָ֨ה ׀ הוֹשִׁ֘יעֵ֤נִי אֱלֹהַ֗י כִּֽי־הִכִּ֣יתָ אֶת־כׇּל־אֹיְבַ֣י לֶ֑חִי שִׁנֵּ֖י רְשָׁעִ֣ים שִׁבַּֽרְתָּ׃ לַֽיהֹוָ֥ה הַיְשׁוּעָ֑ה עַֽל־עַמְּךָ֖ בִרְכָתֶ֣ךָ סֶּֽלָה׃

</he>
        <trans>Mizmor ledavid bevor?cho mipenê Avshalom beno
Adonai ma rabu tsarai, rabim camim alai
Rabim omerim lenafshi, ên ieshuáta lo velohim sêla
Veata Adonai maguen baadi, kevodi umerim roshi
Coli el Adonai ecrá, vaiaaneni mehar codsho sêla
Ani shachavti vaishána, hekitsoti ki Adonai yismecheni
Lo ira merivevot am, asher saviv shátu alai
Cuma Adonai hoshiêni Elohai, ki hikita et col oievai lechi, shinê reshaim shibarta
Ladonai haishuá, al amechá virchatêcha sêla</trans>
</string>
<string id ="4">
        <en>For the leader; with instrumental music. A psalm of David.
Answer me when I call,
O God, my vindicator!
You freed me from distress;
have mercy on me and hear my prayer.
You who side against me, how long will my glory be mocked,
will you love illusions,
have recourse to frauds?    Selah.
Know that GOD keeps the faithful close;
 GOD hears when I call out.
So tremble, and sin no more;
ponder it on your bed, and sigh.    Selah.
Offer sacrifices in righteousness
and trust in GOD.
Many say, ?O for good days!?
Bestow Your favor on us, O ETERNAL One.
You put joy into my heart
when their grain and wine show increase.
Safe and sound, I lie down and sleep,
for You alone, O ETERNAL One, keep me secure.
</en>
        <he></he>
        <trans>Lamnatsêach binguinot mizmor ledavid
Becor?í aneni Elohê tsidki, batsar hir?chavta li, choneni ushemá tefilati        
Benê ish, ad mé chevodi lichlima teehavun ric, tevac?shú chazav sêla
Udeú ki hifla Adonai chassid lo, Adonai yishmá becor?í elav
Rigzu veal techetáu, imru vilvavechem al mish?cavchem vedômu sêla
Zivechu zivechê tsédec, uvitchú el Adonai
Rabim omerim mi iar?ênu tov, nessa alênu or panêcha Adonai
Natáta simcha velibi, meet deganam vetirosham rábu
Beshalom iachdav eshkevá veishan, ki ata Adonai levadad lavêtach toshivêni</trans>
</string>
<string id ="5">
        <en>For the leader; on ne?iloth. A psalm of David.
Give ear to my speech, O ETERNAL One;
consider my utterance.
Heed the sound of my cry,
my Sovereign and God,
for I pray to You.
Hear my voice, O ETERNAL One, at daybreak;
at daybreak I plead before You, and wait.
For You are not a God who desires wickedness;
evil cannot abide with You;
the wanton cannot endure in Your sight.
You detest all evildoers;
You doom those who speak lies;
deceitful murderers GOD abhors.
But I, through Your abundant love, enter Your house;
I bow down in awe at Your holy temple.
O ETERNAL One, lead me along Your righteous [path]
because of my watchful foes;
make Your way straight before me.
For there is no sincerity on their lips;
their heart is [filled with] malice;
their throat is an open grave;
their tongue slippery.
Condemn them, O God;
let them fall by their own devices;
cast them out for their many crimes,
for they defy You.
But let all who take refuge in You rejoice,
ever jubilant as You shelter them;
and let those who love Your name exult in You.
For You surely bless the righteous, O ETERNAL One,
encompassing them with favor like a shield.
</en>
        <he></he>
        <trans>Lamnatsêach el hanechilót mizmor ledavid
Amarai haazina, Adonai, biná haguigui
Hac?shiva lecol shav?i malki velohai, ki elêcha etpalal
Adonai, boker tishmá coli, boker eerach lechá vaatsape
Ki lo El chafets résha, áta, lo iegurechá rá
Lo yit?iatsevu holelim lenégued enêcha, saneta col pôale áven
Teabed doverê chazav, ish damim umirma ietaev, Adonai
Vaani berov chasdechá avô vetêcha eshtachavê el hechal codshechá beyir?atêcha    
Adonai necheni vetsidcatêcha lemaan shorerai, haishar lefanai darkêcha
Ki ên befihu nechona, kirbam havót, kéver patúach gueronam, leshonam iachalicun  
Haashimem Elohim, yipelu mimoatsotehem, berov pish?ehem hadichemo ki máru vach   
Veyismechu chol chossê vach, leolam ieranênu, vetassech alemo, veialetsu vechá ohavê shemêcha
Ki ata tevarech tsadic Adonai, catsiná ratson taterênu</trans>
</string>
<string id ="6">
        <en>For the leader; with instrumental music on the sheminith. A psalm of David.
O ETERNAL One, do not punish me in anger,
do not chastise me in fury.
Have mercy on me, O ETERNAL One, for I languish;
heal me, O ETERNAL One, for my bones shake with terror.
My whole being is stricken with terror,
while You, ETERNAL One?O, how long!
O ETERNAL One, turn! Rescue me!
Deliver me as befits Your faithfulness.
For there is no praise of You among the dead;
in Sheol, who can acclaim You?
I am weary with groaning;
every night I drench my bed,
I melt my couch in tears.
My eyes are wasted by vexation,
worn out because of all my foes.
Away from me, all you evildoers,
for GOD heeds the sound of my weeping.
GOD heeds my plea,
 GOD accepts my prayer.
All my enemies will be frustrated and stricken with terror;
they will turn back in an instant, frustrated.
</en>
        <he></he>
        <trans>Lamnatsêach binguinot al hasheminit mizmor ledavid
Adonai al beapechá tochichêni, veal bachamatechá teiasserêni
Chonênu Adonai, ki umlal áni, refaêni Adonai, ki niv?halu atsamai
Venafshi niv?halá meod, veata Adonai ad matai
Shuva Adonai, chaletsá nafshi, hoshiêni lemaan chasdêcha
Ki en bamávet zich?rêcha, bisheol mi iode lach
Iagáti veanchati, as?che vechol laila mitati, bedim?ati arsi amsê
Ashesha micáas eni, ateca bechol tsorerai
Súru mimeni col pôale áven, ki shamá Adonai col bichyi
Shamá Adonai techinati, Adonai tefilati yicach
Ievôshu veyibahalu meod col oievai, iashúvu ievôshu rága</trans>
</string>
<string id ="7">
        <en>Shiggaion of David, which he sang to GOD, concerning Cush, a Benjaminite.
O my ETERNAL God, in You I seek refuge;
deliver me from all my pursuers and save me,
lest, like a lion, they tear me apart,
rending in pieces, and no one save me.
O my ETERNAL God, if I have done such things,
if my hands bear the guilt of wrongdoing,
if I have dealt evil to my ally?
I who rescued my foe without reward?
then let the enemy pursue and overtake me;
let my life be trampled to the ground,
and my body dwell in the dust.    Selah.
Rise, O ETERNAL One, in Your anger;
assert Yourself against the fury of my foes;
bestir Yourself in my behalf;
You have ordained judgment.
 Let the assembly of peoples gather about You,
with You enthroned above, on high.
GOD judges the peoples;
vindicate me, O ETERNAL One,
for the righteousness and blamelessness that are mine.
Let the evil of the wicked come to an end,
but establish the righteous;
the One who probes the mind and conscience is God the Righteous.
I look to God to shield me;
the deliverer of the upright.
God vindicates the righteous;
God pronounces doom each day.
If someone [wicked] does not turn back, but whets his sword,
bends his bow and aims it,
then against himself he readies deadly weapons,
and makes his arrows sharp.
See, he hatches evil, conceives mischief,
and gives birth to fraud.
He has dug a pit and deepened it,
and will fall into the trap he made.
His mischief will recoil upon his own head;
his lawlessness will come down upon his skull.
I will praise GOD for being righteous,
and sing a hymn to the name of GOD Most High.
</en>
        <he></he>
        <trans>Shigaion ledavid asher shar ladonai al divrê Chush ben Iemini     
Adonai Elohai bechá chassíti, hoshiêni micol rodefai vehatsilêni
Pen yitrof keariê nafshi, porec veen matsil
Adonai Elohai, im assiti zot, im iesh ável bechapai
Im gamalti sholemi rá, vaachaletsá tsoreri recam
Yiradof oiev nafshi veiasseg veyirmos laárets chaiai, uch?vodi leafar iashken sêla
Cuma Adonai beapêcha, hinasse beavrot tsorerai, veúra elai, mishpat tsivíta      
Vaadat leumim tessovevêca, vealêha lamarom shúva
Adonai iadin amim, shofteni Adonai ketsidki uchtumi alai
Yigmor na ra reshaim, utechonen tsadic uvochen libót uchlaiót Elohim tsadic      
Maguiní al Elohim, moshia yishrê lev
Elohim shofet tsadic, veel zoem bechol iom
Im lo iashuv, charbo yiltosh, cashto darach vaichonenêha
Velo hechin kelê mávet, chitsav ledolekim yif?al
Hine iechabel áven, vehara amal veialad sháker
Bor cara vaiachperêhu, vayipol beshachat yif?al
Iashuv amalo verosho, veal codcodo chamasso iered
Odê Adonai ketsidco, vaazamera shem Adonai elion</trans>
</string>
<string id ="8">
        <en>For the leader; on the gittith. A psalm of David.
O ETERNAL One, our Sovereign,
how majestic is Your name throughout the earth?
You who have covered the heavens with Your splendor!
 From the mouths of infants and sucklings
You have founded strength on account of Your foes,
to put an end to enemy and avenger.
When I behold Your heavens, the work of Your fingers,
the moon and stars that You set in place,
what are human beings that You have been mindful of them,
mortals that You have taken note of them,
that You have made them little less than divine,
and adorned them with glory and majesty?
You have made them master over Your handiwork,
laying the world at their feet?
sheep and oxen, all of them,
and wild beasts, too;
the birds of the heavens, the fish of the sea,
whatever travels the paths of the seas.
O ETERNAL One, our Sovereign, how majestic is Your name throughout the earth!    
</en>
        <he></he>
        <trans>Lamnatsêach al haguitit mizmor ledavid
Adonai Adonênu, ma adir shimchá bechol haárets, asher tena hodechá al hashamáyim 
Mipi olelim veionekim yissadta oz, lemaan tsorerêcha, lehashbit oiev umitnakem   
Ki er?e shamêcha maasse ets?beotêcha, iarêach vechochavim asher conanta
Ma enósh ki tizkerênu, uven adam ki tifkedenu
Vatechasserêhu meat meelohim, vechavod vehadar teaterêhu
Tamshilêhu bemaassê iadêcha, col sháta tachat raglav
Tsone vaalafim culam, vegam bahamot sadai
Tsipor shamáyim udeguê haiam, over orchót iamim
Adonai Adonênu, ma adir shimchá bechol haárets</trans>
</string>
<string id ="9">
        <en>For the leader; ?almuth labben. A psalm of David.
I will praise You, ETERNAL One, with all my heart;
I will tell all Your wonders.
I will rejoice and exult in You,
singing a hymn to Your name, O Most High.
When my enemies retreat,
they stumble to their doom at Your presence.
For You uphold my right and claim,
enthroned as righteous judge.
You blast the nations;
You destroy the wicked;
You blot out their name forever.
 The enemy is no more?
ruins everlasting;
You have torn down their cities;
their very names are lost.
But GOD, whose throne is set up for judgment, abides forever;
it is [God] who judges the world with righteousness,
rules the peoples with equity.
GOD is a haven for the oppressed,
a haven in times of trouble.
Those who know Your name trust You,
for You do not abandon those who turn to You, O ETERNAL One.
Sing a hymn to the ETERNAL, who reigns in Zion;
declare God?s deeds among the peoples.
For [God] does not ignore the cry of the afflicted;
the One who requites bloodshed is mindful of them.
Have mercy on me, O ETERNAL One;
see my affliction at the hands of my foes,
You who lift me from the gates of death,
so that in the gates of Fair Zion
I might tell all Your praise,
I might exult in Your deliverance.
The nations sink in the pit they have made;
their own foot is caught in the net they have hidden.
GOD is known,
having worked judgment;
the wicked are snared by their own devices. Higgaion.    Selah.       
Let the wicked be in Sheol,
all the nations who ignore God!
Not always shall the needy be ignored,
nor the hope of the afflicted forever lost.
Rise, O ETERNAL One!
Let not mortals have power;
let the nations be judged in Your presence.
Strike fear into them, O ETERNAL One;
let the nations know they are only mortals.    Selah.
</en>
        <he></he>
        <trans>Lamnatsêach al mut Laben mizmor ledavid
Odê Adonai bechol libi, assaperá col nifleotêcha
Esmechá veeeltsá vach, azamera shimchá elion
Beshuv oievai achor, yicashelú veiovedú mipanêcha
Ki assita mishpati vedini, iashavta lechisse shofet tsédec
Gaárta goyim, ibadta rashá, shemam machita leolam vaed
Haoiev tamu choravót lanétsach, vearim natashta, avad zich?ram hema   
Vadonai leolam ieshev, conen lamishpat kis?o
Vehu yishpot tevel betsédec, iadin leumim bemesharim
Vihi Adonai misgav ladach, misgav leitot batsará
Veyiv?techú vechá iodeê shemêcha, ki lo azavta doreshêcha Adonai      
Zamerú ladonai ioshev Tsión, haguídu vaamim alilotav
Ki doresh damim otam zachar, lo shachach tsaacat anavim
Choneneni Adonai, ree onyi missoneai, meromemi mishaarê mávet
Lemaan assaperá col tehilatêcha beshaarê vat Tsión, aguila bishuatêcha
Taveú goyim beshachat assu, beréshet zu tamanu nilkeda raglam
Nodá Adonai mishpat assá, befoal capav nokesh rashá, higaion sêla     
Iashuvu reshaim lish?ola, col goyim shechechê Elohim
Ki lo lanétsach yishachach evion, tic?vat aniyim tovad laad
Cuma Adonai al iaoz enósh, yishafetu goyim al panêcha
Shita Adonai morá lahem, iedeú goyim enósh hema sêla</trans>
</string>
<string id ="10">
        <en>Why, O ETERNAL One, do You stand aloof,
heedless in times of trouble?
The wicked in their arrogance hound the lowly?
may they be caught in the schemes they devise!
The wicked crow about their unbridled lusts;
the grasping revile and scorn GOD.
The wicked, arrogant as they are,
in all their scheming [think],
?God does not care
and does not call to account.?
Their ways prosper at all times;
Your judgments are far beyond them;
they snort at all their foes.
Such people think, ?I shall not be shaken,
through all time never be in trouble.?
Their mouth is full of oaths, deceit, and fraud;
mischief and evil are under their tongue.
They lurk in outlying places;
from a covert they slay the innocent;
their eyes spy out the hapless.
They wait in a covert like a lion in a lair;
wait to seize the lowly;
they seize the lowly as they pull their net shut;
they stoop, they crouch,
and the hapless fall prey to their might.
They think, ?God is not mindful,
the divine face is hidden and never looks.?
Rise, O ETERNAL One!
Strike at them, O God!
Do not forget the lowly.
Why should the wicked scorn God,
thinking You do not call to account?
You do look!
You take note of mischief and vexation!
To requite is in Your power.
To You the hapless can entrust themselves;
You have ever been the orphans? help.
O break the power of the wicked and evildoers,
so that when You look for their wickedness
You will find it no more.
GOD is sovereign for ever and ever;
the nations will perish from this land.
You will listen to the entreaty of the lowly, O ETERNAL One,
You will make their hearts firm;
You will incline Your ear
to champion the orphan and the downtrodden,
that mere earthly mortals tyrannize no more.
</en>
        <he></he>
        <trans>Lama Adonai taamod berachoc, talim leitot batsará      
Begaavat rasha yidlac ani, yitafessu bimzimót zu chashávu
Ki hilel rashá al taavat nafsho, uvotsêa bérech niets, Adonai
Rashá kegova apo bal yidrosh, en Elohim col mezimotav
Iachilu derachav bechol et, marom mishpatêcha minegdo, col tsorerav iafiach bahem
Amar belibo bal emot, ledor vador asher lo verá
Ala pihu male umirmót vatoch, tachat leshono amal vaáven
Ieshev bemarav chatserim, bemistarim iaharog naki, enav lechelechá yitsponu
Ieerov bamistar kearie vessuco, ieerov lachatof ani, iach?tof ani bemosh?cho verishto
Yideke iashôach, venafal baatsumav chel caím
Amar belibo shachach El, histir panav bal raa lanétsach
Cuma Adonai, El nessa iadêcha, al tish?cach anavim
Al me niets rashá, Elohim, amar belibo lo tidrosh
Raíta ki ata amal vachaas tabit, latet beiadêcha, alêcha iaazov chelêcha, iatom ata hayita ozer
Shevor zerôa rashá, vará tidrosh rish?o val timtsa
Adonai mélech olam vaed, avedu goyim meartso
Taavat anavim shamata Adonai, tachin libam tac?shiv oznêcha
Lishpot iatom vadach, bal iossif od laarots enósh min haárets</trans> 
</string>
<string id ="11">
        <en>For the leader. Of David.
In GOD I take refuge;
how can you say to me,
?Take to the hills like a bird!
For see, the wicked bend the bow,
they set their arrow on the string
to shoot from the shadows at the upright.
When the foundations are destroyed,
what can the righteous do??
 GOD is in the divine holy palace;
 GOD?whose throne is in heaven,
whose eyes behold, whose gaze searches humankind.
GOD seeks out someone righteous,
but loathes the wicked one who loves injustice.
[God] will rain down upon the wicked blazing coals and sulfur;        
a scorching wind shall be their lot.
For GOD is righteous,
and loves righteous deeds;
the upright shall behold God?s face.
</en>
        <he></he>
        <trans>Lamnatsêach ledavid, badonai chassiti, ech tomeru lenafshi núdi harchem tsipor
Ki hine hareshaim yidrechun késhet, conenu chitsam al iéter, lirot bemo ofel leyishrê lev
Ki hashatot ieharessun, tsadic ma paal
Adonai behechal codsho Adonai bashamáyim kis?o, enav iechezu, af?apav yivchanu benê adam
Adonai tsadic yivchan, verashá veohev chamas sanea nafsho
Iamter al reshaim pachim esh vegofrit, veruach zil?afót menat cossam  
Ki tsadic Adonai, tsedacot ahev, iashar iechezu fanemo</trans>        
</string>
<string id ="12">
        <en>For the leader; on the sheminith. A psalm of David.       
Help, O ETERNAL One!
For the faithful are no more;
the loyal have vanished from among mortals.
People speak lies to one another;
their speech is smooth;
they talk with duplicity.
May GOD cut off all flattering lips,
every tongue that speaks arrogance.
They say, ?By our tongues we shall prevail;
with lips such as ours, who can be our master??
?Because of the groans of the plundered poor and needy,
I will now act,? says GOD.
?I will give help,? [God] affirms to them.
GOD?s words are pure words,
silver purged in an earthen crucible,
refined sevenfold.
You, O ETERNAL One, will keep them,
guarding each from this age evermore.
On every side the wicked roam
when baseness is exalted among mortals.
</en>
        <he></he>
        <trans>Lamnatsêach al hasheminit mizmor ledavid
Hoshía Adonai ki gamar chassid, ki fassu emunim mibenê adam
Shav iedaberú ish et reêhu, sefat chalacót, belev valev iedabêru      
Iach?ret Adonai col siftê chalacót, lashon medabéret guedolót
Asher ameru lileshonênu nagbir sefatênu itánu, mi adon lánu
Mishod aniyim meencat evionim, ata acum iomar Adonai, ashit beiêsha iafíach lo
Imerot Adonai amarot tehorot, késsef tsaruf, baalil laárets mezucac shiv?atáyim
Ata Adonai tishmerem, titserênu min hador zu leolam
Saviv reshaim yit?haláchun, kerum zulut livnê adam</trans>
</string>
<string id ="13">
        <en>For the leader. A psalm of David.
How long, O ETERNAL One; will You ignore me forever?
How long will You hide Your face from me?
How long will I have cares on my mind,
grief in my heart all day?
How long will my enemy have the upper hand?
Look at me, answer me, O my ETERNAL God!
Restore the luster to my eyes,
lest I sleep the sleep of death;
lest my enemy say, ?I have overcome him,?
my foes exult when I totter.
But I trust in Your faithfulness,
my heart will exult in Your deliverance.
I will sing to GOD,
who has been good to me.
</en>
        <he></he>
        <trans>Lamnatsêach mizmor ledavid
Ad ána Adonai tishcachêni nétsach, ad ána tastir et panêcha mimêni    
Ad ána ashit etsot benafshi iagon bilevavi iomam, ad ána iarum oievi alai
Habíta anêni Adonai Elohai, haíra enai pen ishan hamávet
Pen iomar oivi iechaltiv, tsarai iaguílu ki emot
Vaani bechasdechá vatáchti, iaguel libi bishuatêcha, ashíra ladonai ki gamal alai</trans>
</string>
<string id ="14">
        <en> For the leader. Of David.
The scoundrel thinks,
?God does not care.?
Human deeds are corrupt and loathsome;
no one does good.
GOD looks down from heaven on humankind
to find someone with understanding,
someone mindful of God.
All have turned bad,
altogether foul;
there is no one who does good,
not even one.
Are they so witless, all those evildoers,
who devour my people as they devour food,
and do not invoke GOD?
There they will be seized with fright,
for God is present in the circle of the righteous.
You may set at naught the counsel of the lowly,
but GOD is their refuge.
O that the deliverance of Israel might come from Zion!
When GOD restores the fortunes of this covenanted people,
Jacob will exult, Israel will rejoice.
</en>
        <he></he>
        <trans>Lamnatsêach ledavid, amar naval belibo en Elohim, hish?chítu hit?ívu alila en osse tov
Adonai mishamáyim hishkif al benê adam, lir?ot haiesh maskil, doresh et Elohim
Hacol sar, iachdav neeláchu, en osse tov, en gam echad
Halo iadeú col pôale áven, ochelê ami achelu léchem, Adonai lo caráu  
Sham pachadu fachad, ki Elohim bedor tsadic
Atsat ani tavíshu, ki Adonai mach?sehu
Mi yiten mitsión ieshuat Yisrael, beshuv Adonai shevut amo, iaguel Iaacov yismach Yisrael</trans>
</string>
<string id ="15">
        <en>A psalm of David.
 GOD, who may sojourn in Your tent,
who may dwell on Your holy mountain?
Anyone who lives without blame,
who does what is right,
and in their heart acknowledges the truth;
whose tongue is not given to evil;
who has never done harm to a compatriot,
or borne reproach for [acts toward] a neighbor;
for whom someone contemptible is abhorrent,
but who honors those who fear GOD;
who keeps an oath even when it hurts;
who has never lent money at interest,
or accepted a bribe against the innocent.
One who acts thus shall never be shaken.
</en>
        <he></he>
        <trans>Mizmor ledavid, Adonai mi iagur beaholêcha, mi yishcon behar codshêcha
Holech tamim ufoel tsédec, vedover emét bilevavo
Lo ragal al leshono, lo assa lereêhu raá, vecherpa lo nassa al kerovo 
Nivze beenav nim?as, veet yir?e Adonai iechabed, nishba lehará velo iamir
Caspo lo natan benéshech, veshochad al naki lo lacach, osse êle lo yimot leolam</trans>
</string>
<string id ="16">
        <en>A michtam of David.
Protect me, O God, for I seek refuge in You.
I say to GOD,
?You are my Sovereign, my benefactor;
there is none above You.?
As to the holy and mighty ones that are in the land,
my whole desire concerning them is that
those who espouse another [god]
may have many sorrows!
I will have no part of their bloody libations;
their names will not pass my lips.
GOD is my allotted share and portion;
You control my fate.
Delightful country has fallen to my lot;
lovely indeed is my estate.
I bless GOD who has guided me;
my conscience admonishes me at night.
I am ever mindful of GOD?s presence?
who is at my right hand; I shall never be shaken.
So my heart rejoices,
my whole being exults,
and my body rests secure.
For You will not abandon me to Sheol,
or let Your faithful one see the Pit.
You will teach me the path of life.
In Your presence is perfect joy;
delights are ever in Your right hand.
</en>
        <he></he>
        <trans>Michtam ledavid, shamerêni El ki chassiti vach
Amart ladonai, Adonai áta, tovati bal alêcha
Licdoshim asher baárets hêma, veadire col cheftsi vam
Yirbu atsevotam, acher maharu, bal assich niskehem midam, uval essa et shemotam al sefatai
Adonai menat chelki vechossi, ata tomich gorali
Chavalim nafelu li baneimim, af nachalat shafera alai
Avarech et Adonai asher iaatsáni, af lelot yisserúni chil?iotai       
Shivíti Adonai lenegdi tamid, ki mimini bal emot
Lachen samach libi vaiáguel kevodi, af bessari yishcon lavêtach       
Ki lo taazov nafshi lish?ol, lo titen chassidechá lir?ot shachat      
Todiêni orach chayim, sóva semachot et panêcha, neimot biminechá nétsach</trans>
</string>
<string id ="17">
        <en>A prayer of David.
Hear, O ETERNAL One, what is just;
heed my cry, give ear to my prayer,
uttered without guile.
My vindication will come from You;
Your eyes will behold what is right.
You have visited me at night, probed my mind,
You have tested me and found nothing amiss;
I determined that my mouth should not transgress.
As for mortals? dealings,
in accord with the command of Your lips,
I have kept in view the fate of the lawless.
My feet have held to Your paths;
my legs have not given way.
I call on You;
You will answer me, God;
turn Your ear to me,
hear what I say.
Display Your faithfulness in wondrous deeds,
You who deliver with Your right hand
those who seek refuge from assailants.
Guard me like the apple of Your eye;
hide me in the shadow of Your wings
from the wicked who despoil me,
my mortal enemies who encircle me.
Their hearts are closed to pity;
they mouth arrogance;
now they hem in our feet on every side;
they set their eyes roaming over the land.
They are like a lion eager for prey,
a king of beasts lying in wait.
Rise, O ETERNAL One! Go forth to meet my enemies.
Bring them down;
rescue me from the wicked with Your sword,
from mortals, O ETERNAL One, with Your hand,
from mortals whose share in life is fleeting.
But as to Your treasured ones,
fill their bellies.
Their children too shall be satisfied,
and have something to leave over for their young.
Then I, justified, will behold Your face;
awake, I am filled with the vision of You.
</en>
        <he></he>
        <trans>Tefilá ledavid, shim?á Adonai tsédec, hac?shiva rinati, haazína tefilati belo siftê mirma
Milefanêcha mishpati ietse, enêcha techezêna mesharim
Bachánta libi, pacadeta laila, tseraftáni val timtsá, zamoti bal iaavor pi
Lifeulót adam bidvar sefatêcha, ani shamarti orchot parits
Tamoch ashurai bemaguelotêcha, bal namôtu feamai
Ani keratícha chi taanêni El, hat oznechá li, shemá imrati
Hafle chassadêcha, moshía chossim mimitcomemim biminêcha
Shomreni keishon bat áyin, betsel kenafêcha tastirêni
Mipenê reshaim zu shadúni, oievai benéfesh iakífu alai
Chelbamo sagueru, pimo diberu vegueut
Ashurênu ata sevavúnu, enehem iashítu lintot baárets
Dimiono kearie yich?sof litrof, vechich?fir ioshev bemistarim
Cuma Adonai cademá fanav, hach?riêhu, paletá nafshi merashá charbêcha 
Mimetim iadechá Adonai, mimetim mechéled, chelcam bachayim utsefunchá temale vitnam, yisbeú vanim, vehiníchu yitram leolelehem
Ani betsédec echeze fanêcha, esbeá vehakits temunatêcha</trans>       
</string>
<string id ="18">
        <en> For the leader. Of David, the servant of GOD, who addressed the words of this song to GOD after GOD had saved him from the hands of all his enemies and from the clutches of Saul.
He said:
I adore you, O ETERNAL One, my strength,
O ETERNAL One, my crag, my fortress, my deliverer,
my God, my rock in which I take shelter,
my shield, my mighty champion, my haven.
All praise! I called on GOD
and was delivered from my enemies.
Ropes of Death encompassed me;
torrents of Belial terrified me;
ropes of Sheol encircled me;
snares of Death confronted me.
In my anguish I called on the ETERNAL,
cried out to my God,
who from a heavenly abode heard my voice,
whose ears received my cry.
Then the earth rocked and quaked;
the foundations of the mountains shook?
rocked by divine indignation;
smoke went up from God?s nostrils,
devouring fire from God?s mouth?
live coals blazing forth.
[God] bent the sky and came down,
thick cloud beneath divine feet.
[God] mounted a cherub and flew,
gliding on the wings of the wind.
[God] made darkness a screen?
pavilions of dark thunderheads,
dense clouds of the sky all around.
In the divine brilliance,
hail and fiery coals pierced those clouds.
Then GOD thundered from heaven,
the Most High gave forth voice?
hail and fiery coals?
letting shafts fly, and scattering them;
discharging lightning, and routing them.
The ocean bed was exposed;
the foundations of the world were laid bare
by Your mighty roaring, O ETERNAL One,
at the blast of Your breath.
Reaching down from on high, [God] took me,
drawing me out of the mighty waters?
rescuing me from my fierce enemy,
from foes too strong for me.
They confronted me on the day of my calamity,
but GOD was my support?
bringing me out to freedom,
pleased with me enough to rescue me.
GOD rewarded me according to my merit?
requiting the cleanness of my hands?
for I have kept to the ways of GOD
and have not been guilty before my God;
for I am mindful of all God?s rules
and have not disregarded God?s laws.
I have been blameless toward [God],
and have guarded myself against sinning;
and GOD has requited my merit,
according to the evident cleanness of my hands.
With the loyal, You deal loyally;
with the blameless, blamelessly.
With the pure, You act purely,
and with the perverse, You are wily.
It is You who deliver lowly folk,
but haughty eyes You humble.
It is You who light my lamp;
my ETERNAL God lights up my darkness.
With You, I can rush a barrier;
with my God, I can scale a wall.
The way of God is perfect;
the word of the ETERNAL is pure.
[God] shields all who seek refuge.
Truly, who is a god except the ETERNAL,
who is a rock but our God??
the God who girded me with might,
who made my way secure;
who made my legs like a deer?s,
and set me firmly on the heights;
who trained my hands for battle?
my arms can bend a bow of bronze!
You have granted me the shield of Your protection;
Your right hand has sustained me,
Your care has made me great.
You have let me stride on freely;
my feet have not slipped.
I pursued my enemies and overtook them;
I did not turn back till I destroyed them.
I struck them down,
and they could rise no more;
they lay at my feet.
You have girded me with strength for battle,
brought low my adversaries before me,
made my enemies turn tail before me;
I wiped out my foes.
They cried out, but there was none to deliver;
to GOD, who did not answer them.
I ground them fine as windswept dust;
I trod them flat like dirt of the streets.
You have rescued me from the strife of people;
You have set me at the head of nations;
peoples I knew not must serve me.
At the mere report of me they are submissive;
foreign peoples cower before me.
Foreign peoples lose courage,
and come trembling out of their strongholds.
GOD lives! Blessed is my rock!
Exalted be God, my deliverer,
the God who has vindicated me
and made peoples subject to me,
who rescued me from my enemies,
who raised me clear of my adversaries,
saved me from the lawless opposition!
For this I sing Your praise among the nations, ETERNAL One,
and hymn Your name:
According great victories to Your king,
keeping faith with Your anointed,
with David and his offspring evermore.
</en>
        <he></he>
        <trans>Lamnatsêach leéved Adonai ledavid, asher diber ladonai et divrê hashirá hazot, beiom hitsil Adonai oto micaf col oievav umiyad Shaul
Vaiomar, erchamcha Adonai chizki
Adonai sal?í umetsudati, umefalti, Eli tsuri echesse bo, maguini vekéren yish?i misgabi
Mehulal ecra Adonai, umin oievai ivashêa
Afafuni chevlê mávet, venachalê veliyáal ievaatúni
Chevlê sheol sevavúni, kidemúni mokeshê mávet
Batsar li ecrá Adonai, veel Elohai ashavêa, yishma mehechalo coli, veshav?ati lefanav tavo veoznav
Vatig?ash vatir?ash haárets, umossedê harim yirgázu, vayitgaashu ki chará lo
Alá ashan beapo, veesh mipiv tochel, guechalim baaru mimenu
Vaiet shamáyim vaierad, vaarafel tachat raglav
Vayircav al keruv vaiaof, vaiedê al canfê rúach
Iashet chóshech sitro sevivotav sucato, ches?chat máyim avê shechakim 
Minôga negdo avav averu, barad vegachalê esh
Vaiar?em bashamáyim Adonai, veelion yiten colo, barad vegachalê esh   
Vayishlach chitsav vaifitsem, uvrakim rav vaihumem
Vaierau afikê máyim, vayigalu mossedot tevel, migaaratechá Adonai, minishmat rúach apêcha
Yishlach mimarom yicachêni, iamshêni mimáyim rabim
Iatsilêni meoivi az, umissoneai ki ametsu mimeni
Iecademuni veiom edi, vaiehi Adonai lemish?an li
Vaiotsiêni lamerchav, iechaletsêni ki cháfets bi
Yigmelêni Adonai ketsidki, kevor iadai iashiv li
Ki shamarti darchê Adonai, velo rashati meelohai
Ki chol mishpatav lenegdi, vechucotav lo assir mêni
Vaehi tamim imo, vaeshtamer meavoni
Vaiáshev Adonai li chetsidki, kevor iadai lenégued enav
Im chassid titchassad, im guevar tamim titamam
Im navar titbarar, veim ikesh titpatal
Ki ata am ani toshía, veenáyim ramot tashpil
Ki ata tair neri, Adonai Elohai iaguíha choshki
Ki vechá aruts guedud, uvelohai adaleg shur
Hael tamim darco, imrat Adonai tserufá, maguen hu lechol hachossim bo 
Ki mi Elôha mibal?adê Adonai, umi tsur zulati Elohênu
Hael hameazerêni cháyil, vayiten tamim darki
Meshave raglai caaialot, veal bamotai iaamidêni
Melamed iadai lamilchama, venichata késhet nechushá zerootai
Vatiten li maguen yish?êcha, viminechá tis?adêni, veanvatechá tarbêni 
Tarchiv tsaadi tachtai, velo maadu carsulai
Erdof oievai veassiguem, velo ashuv ad calotam
Emchatsem velo iuchelu cum, yipelu tachat raglai
Vateazerêni cháyil lamilchama, tach?ría camai tachtai
Veoievai natata li óref, umessan?ai atsmitem
Ieshaveú veen moshía, al Adonai velo anam
Veesh?chakem keafar al penê rúach, ketit chutsót arikem
Tefaletêni merivê am, tesimêni lerosh goyim, am ló iadáti iaavdúni    
Leshema ózen yishameu li, benê nechar iechachashu li
Benê nechar yibôlu, veiach?regu mimisguerotehem
Chai Adonai uvaruch tsuri, veiarum Elohê yish?í
Hael hanoten necamót li, vaiadber amim tachtai
Mefaleti meoivai, af min camai teromemêni, meish chamas tatsilêni     
Al ken odechá vagoyim, Adonai, ul?shimchá azamêra
Magdil ieshuot malcó, veosse chéssed limeshicho, ledavid ulezar?ó ad olam</trans>
</string>
<string id ="19">
        <en>For the leader. A psalm of David.
The heavens declare the glory of God,
the sky proclaims God?s handiwork.
Day to day makes utterance,
night to night speaks out.
There is no utterance,
there are no words,
whose sound goes unheard.
Their voice carries throughout the earth,
their words to the end of the world.
[God] placed in them a tent for the sun,
who is like a groom coming forth from the chamber,
like a hero, eager to run his course.
His rising-place is at one end of heaven,
and his circuit reaches the other;
nothing escapes his heat.
The teaching of GOD is perfect,
renewing life;
the decrees of GOD are enduring,
making the simple wise,
The precepts of GOD are just,
rejoicing the heart;
the instruction of GOD is lucid,
making the eyes light up.
The fear of GOD is pure,
abiding forever;
the judgments of GOD are true,
righteous altogether,
more desirable than gold,
than much fine gold;
sweeter than honey,
than drippings of the comb.
Your servant pays them heed;
in obeying them there is much reward.
Who can be aware of errors?
Clear me of unperceived guilt,
and from willful sins keep Your servant;
let them not dominate me;
then shall I be blameless
and clear of grave offense.
May the words of my mouth
and the prayer of my heart
be acceptable to You,
O ETERNAL One, my rock and my redeemer.
</en>
        <he></he>
        <trans>Lamnatsêach mizmor ledavid
Hashamayim messaperim kevod El, umaasse iadav maguid harakía
Iom leiom iabía ômer, velaila lelaila iechave dáat
En ômer veen devarim, beli nishma colam
Bechol haárets iatsa cavam uvictsê tevel milehem, lashémesh sam ohel bahem
Vehu kechatan iotse mechupato, iassis keguibor laruts ôrach
Mictse hashamayim motsaó, utcufato al ketsotam, veen nistar mechamato 
Torat Adonai temima meshívat náfesh, edut Adonai neemana machkímat pêti
Picudê Adonai iesharim messamechê lev, mitsvat Adonai bara meirat enáyim
Yir?at Adonai tehorá omédet laad, mishpetê Adonai emet tsadcú iachdav 
Hanechemadim mizahav umipaz rav, umetukim midevash venofet tsufim     
Gam avdechá niz?har bahem, beshomram ékev rav
Sheguiot mi iavin, ministarot nakêni
Gam mizedim chassoch avdêcha, al yimshelu vi, az etam venikêti mipêsha rav
Yihiu leratson imrê fi veheguion libi lefanêcha, Adonai tsuri vegoali</trans>
</string>
<string id ="20">
        <en>For the leader. A psalm of David.
May GOD answer you in time of trouble,
the name of Jacob?s God keep you safe?
sending you help from the sanctuary,
and sustaining you from Zion.
May [God] receive the tokens of all your grain offerings,
and approve your burnt offerings.    Selah.
May your desire be granted,
your every plan fulfilled.
May we shout for joy in your victory,
arrayed by standards in the name of our God.
May GOD fulfill your every wish.
Now I know that GOD will give victory to our anointed one,
will answer him from the heavenly sanctuary
with the mighty victories of God?s right arm.
They [call] on chariots, they [call] on horses,
but we call on the name of the ETERNAL our God.
They collapse and lie fallen,
but we rally and gather strength.
O ETERNAL One, grant victory to the king;
may [God] answer us when we call.
</en>
        <he></he>
        <trans>Lamnatsêach mizmor ledavid
Iaanchá Adonai beiom tsara, iessaguevchá shem Elohê Iaacov
Yishlach ezrechá micódesh, umitsión yis?adêca
Yizcor col minchotêcha, veolatechá iedashene sêla
Yiten lecha chilvavêcha, vechol atsatechá iemalê
Neranena bishuatêcha, uvshem Elohênu nidgol, iemale Adonai col mish?alotêcha
Ata iadáti, ki hoshía Adonai meshichó, iaanêhu mishemê codsho, bigvurot iêsha iemino
Ele varéchev veele vassussim, vaanáchnu beshem Adonai Elohênu nazkir  
Hêma careu venafálu, vaanáchnu camnu vanit?odad
Adonai hoshía, hamélech iaanênu veiom cor?ênu</trans>
</string>
<string id ="147">
        <en>Hallelujah.
It is good to chant hymns to our God;
it is pleasant to sing glorious praise.
GOD rebuilds Jerusalem,
gathering in the exiles of Israel?
healing their broken hearts,
and binding up their wounds.
[God] reckoned the number of the stars
and gave each its name.
Great and full of power is our Sovereign?
whose wisdom is beyond reckoning.
GOD gives courage to the lowly,
and brings the wicked down to the dust.
Sing to GOD a song of praise,
chant a hymn with a lyre to our God,
who covers the heavens with clouds,
provides rain for the earth,
makes mountains put forth grass;
who gives the beasts their food,
to the raven?s brood what they cry for.
[God] does not prize the strength of horses,       
nor value the warrior?s fleetness;
but GOD values those who show reverence,
those who depend on God?s faithful care.
O Jerusalem, glorify GOD;
praise your God, O Zion!
For the bars of your gates have been made strong,  
and your children have been blessed within you.    
Your realm has been endowed with well-being,       
and you have been satisfied with choice wheat.     
[God] sends forth words to the earth
with swift commands.
[God] lays down snow like fleece,
scatters frost like ashes.
[God] tosses down hail like crumbs?
who can endure such icy cold?
[God] issues a command?it melts them;
breathes, and the waters flow.
Divine commands were issued to Jacob,
God?s statutes and rules to Israel.
This was not done for any other nation;
of such rules they know nothing.
Hallelujah.
</en>
        <he></he>
        <trans>Halelu Iá, ki tov zamerá Elohênu, ki naím nava tehila
Bone Ierushaláyim Adonai, nidchê Yisrael iechanes  
Harofe lishvurê lev, umchabesh leatsevotam
Monê mispar lacochavim, lechulam shemot yicra      
Gadol adonênu verav côach, litvunato en mispar     
Meoded anavim Adonai, mashpil reshaim adê árets    
Enu ladonai betoda, zamerú lelohênu vechinor       
Hamechassê shamáyim beavim, hamechin laárets matar, hamatsmíach harim chatsir
Noten livehema lachma, livnê orev asher yicráu     
Lo vigvurat hassus iechpats, lo veshokê haish yirtse
Rotse Adonai et iereav, et hameiachalim lechasdo   
Shabechi Ierushaláyim et Adonai, haleli Eloháyich Tsión
Ki chizak berichê shearáyich, berach banáyich bekirbêch
Hassam guevulêch shalom, chélev chitim iasbiech    
Hasholêach imrato árets, ad meherá iaruts devaro   
Hanoten shéleg catsámer, kefor caéfer iefazer      
Mashlich carcho chefitim, lifnê carato mi iaamod   
Yishlach devaro veiamsem, iashev rucho yizelú máyim
Maguid devarav leiaacov, chucav umishpatav leyisrael
Lo ássa chen lechol goi, umishpatim bal iedaum, halelu Iá

</trans>
</string>

<string id ="148">
        <en>Hallelujah.
Praise GOD from the heavens;
give praise on high.
Give praise, all you angels,
give praise, all divine hosts.
Give praise, sun and moon,
give praise, all bright stars.
Give praise, highest heavens,
and you waters that are above the heavens.
Let them praise the name of GOD?
who commanded that they be created,
and who made them endure forever,
establishing an order that shall never change.     
Praise GOD, O you who are on earth,
all sea monsters and ocean depths,
fire and hail, snow and smoke,
storm wind that executes God?s command,
all mountains and hills,
all fruit trees and cedars,
all wild and tamed animals,
creeping things and winged birds,
all kings and peoples of the earth,
all princes of the earth and its judges,
youths and maidens alike,
old and young together.
Let them praise GOD?s name?
for sublime is this name alone?
of the One whose splendor covers heaven and earth. 
[God] has exalted the horn of this people
for the glory of all faithful ones,
Israel, the people brought close.
Hallelujah.
</en>
        <he></he>
        <trans>Halelu Iá, halelú et Adonai min hashamáyim, haleluhú bameromim
Haleluhú chol mal?achav, haleluhú col tsevaav      
Haleluhú shémesh veiarêach, haleluhú col côchve or 
Haleluhú shemê shamáyim, vehamáayim asher meal hashamáyim
Iehalelu et shem Adonai, ki hu tsiva venivráu      
Vaiaamidem laad leolam, choc natan veló iaavor     
Halelu et Adonai min haárets, taninim vechol tehomot
Esh uvarad, shéleg vekitor, rúach seará ossa devaro
Heharim vechol guevaot, ets peri vechol arazim     
Hachaia vechol behema, rémes vetsipor canaf        
Malchê érets vechol leumim, sarim vechol shôfete árets
Bachurim vegam betulot, zekenim im nearim
Iehalelu et shem Adonai, ki nisgav shemo levado, hodô al érets veshamáyim
Vaiárem kéren leamo, tehila lechol chassidav, livnê Yisrael am kerovo, halelu Iá</trans>
</string>

<string id ="149">
        <en>Hallelujah.
Sing to GOD a new song,
sing praises in the congregation of the faithful.  
Let Israel rejoice in its maker;
let the children of Zion exult in their monarch.   
Let them praise God?s name in dance;
with hand-drum and lyre let them chant such praises.
For GOD delights in this people,
and adorns the lowly with victory.
Let the faithful exult in glory;
let them shout for joy upon their couches,
with paeans to God in their throats
and two-edged swords in their hands,
to impose retribution upon the nations,
punishment upon the peoples,
binding their kings with shackles,
their nobles with chains of iron,
executing the doom decreed against them.
This is the glory of all the faithful.
Hallelujah.
</en>
        <he></he>
        <trans>Halelu Iá, shíru ladonai shir chadash, tehilato bikehal chassidim
Yismach Yisrael beossav, benê Tsión iaguílu vemalcam
Iehalelu shemo vemachol, betof vechinor iezamerú lo
Ki rotsê Adonai amo, iefaer anavim bishuá
Ialezu chassidim bechavod, ieranenu al mishkevotam 
Romemot el bigronam, vechérev pifiyot beiadam      
Lassot necama bagoyim, tochechot baleumin
Lessor malchehem bezikim, venichbedehem bechavelê varzel
Laassot bahem mishpat catuv, hadar hu lechol chassidav, halelu Iá</trans>
</string>

<string id ="150">
        <en>Hallelujah.
Give praise in the divine sanctuary;
give praise in the sky, the divine stronghold. 
Give praise for mighty acts;
give praise for exceeding greatness. 
Give praise with blasts of the horn;
give praise with harp and lyre.
Give praise with hand-drum and dance;
give praise with lute and pipe.
Give praise with resounding cymbals;
give praise with loud-clashing cymbals.
Let all that breathes praise Yah.
Hallelujah.
</en>
        <he></he>
        <trans>Halelu Iá, halelú El becodsho, haleluhú birkía uzo
Haleluhú vigvurotav, haleluhú kerov gudlo
Haleluhú betéca shofar, haleluhú benével vechinor
Haleluhú betof umachol, haleluhú beminim veugav
Haleluhú vetsil?tselê sháma, haleluhú betsil?tselê teruá
Col haneshamá tehalel Iá, halelu Iá

</trans>
</string>

</Resources>


